this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
door / software this is your hand
espresso radio we have another episode
with Rachel a cop and maximum and I will
start with reading the biographies
Rachael Leigh Cook is a market principle
for Saltworks New York she works mainly
as a technical lead and architect her
work is to help clients to introduce
continuous delivery in the software
workflow she's editor in chief of the p3
magazine and monthly online magazine
about technical excellence
she is also member of the sort works
technical advisor birds which meets
regularly to produce the sort works
technical writer
welcome to the show right sorry thank
you
nice to be here max Lincoln is a
continuous delivery lead consultants for
Salt Works New York he passionately
promotes the use of continuous delivery
and DevOps to achieve technical success
he's a frequent contributor to open
source cloud quality issuance and
documentation projects such as the
windows support for Travis CI and the
vagrant plugin for Express welcome to
the show max thank you so yeah why don't
we start with Rachel is there anything
you want to add to your biography only
that it's the p2 magazine not--these
sorry alright max just that the window
stuff for Travis CI it's still a work in
progress but hopefully we'll make some
good progress and I'm hoping they'll be
Windows support in the future so let's
start with a very basic question what is
continuous delivery on Windows
or what is continuous delivery and why
do you need to do on Windows Wow answer
that one that one question livery is
about getting putting the ability to
release back in the hands of the
business by making your software putting
your software into a state that it's
always releasable and that and there's a
lot of practice in order to make
something like always the poly ball
always ready for release and that
includes everything from automating the
Quality Assurance the way that you
architecture system in small enough
pieces to be able to deliver in terms of
how you manage your releases in terms of
continuous integration and constant
check-ins that have tests against them
and compiled and this is happening
everyday all day
regular check-ins in terms of info
meaning your deployments and then
automating the standing up of your
infrastructure and so there's and also
in terms of like how you stuck to your
organization to be able to release
rapidly and have that flexibility within
the processes that you have so there's a
lot to continue so they've really build
on top of a lot of other practices like
automation in terms of QA and automation
of infrastructure and automation of
deployments and it built on a lot of
other things so it's quite a broad scope
or that's why I laugh when I say what is
continuous delivery because it's quite a
lot and I think a lot of people think
it's think it's in it that's the way
it's it's the same as DevOps but it's
not there's a lot more to it there and
then what is it on Windows and it's the
reason we call out window specifically
is just because a lot of that automation
is just a little bit harder on Windows
and it's not it doesn't have the same
level of support that you get on Linux
environments for me the difference
between continuous delivery and
continuous integration is with
continuous integration you just have
usually build that sort of is all of
your tests for the project and when you
look at it it's a process and it's
automation but there's a big cultural
piece that goes along with both so when
organizations start doing CI a lot of
times the main question on everyone's
mind is is the build green let's keep
the build green all that stuff I think
continuous delivery even though you
still have pipelines you're trying to
keep green it changes it because the end
goal is really deploying and it's not
just keeping the software tested and
keeping that green it's the entire flow
from the testing in different phases so
you can get feedback in phases but the
security performance testing sign offs
from the business whatever has to happen
so I think for teams doing CI the
question in their mind a lot of time as
is the build still green and for
continuous delivery teams I think a lot
of times that's how long has it been
since we released and it changes but
your perspective of especially in a
development team of of what you're
building it's no more longer just about
development it's like how does it run in
production in terms of it like
performance and load and and all that
you start having to really care about
these concerns because you you're
releasing all the time actually I
remember when I joined sort works
because you talked a little bit a lot
about continuous integration there was
this continuous delivery talk on can you
elaborate on what continuous integration
actually means and where continuous
delivery goes beyond it well for me one
interesting thing is a lot of the stuff
I've been working on recently is more
libraries instead of applications and so
when I'm building just a tool or a
library ci is still most of the time
always sort of really need but what what
is CI actually CI is a it's continuous
integration it's the practice of
continually integrating so some of the
practices involved in CI are things like
trunk based development so don't have
like an everlasting feature branch
that's going to cause you an incredible
amount of pain when you're merging it's
about the developers checking in all the
time and that whole build green thing is
is what makes the build green right it's
that all the unit tests pass all the
integration tests that pass all the
functional level tests
on every check-in and you guys are
checking in regularly and you have a
pipeline of tests that give you the
confidence that your check-in isn't
breaking anything because it's all about
fast feedback so it's continually
integrate to get fast feedback on your
changes yeah I think the big goal with
continuous delivery is to not get stuck
in the last mile before releasing and I
think continuous integration tries to
take care of making sure there's no
merge shell where you've got different
teams doing different things and they
try and bring the code together at the
last minute and they find conflicting
changes but I think with continuous
delivery you still have that part of it
you're doing the CI - turned void merge
shell but you're bringing in other
things like security and usability
testing or whatever into the mix I think
it builds on top of so when people when
I often get upset when people think
continuous delivery is just DevOps
because you actually need the practice
of CI in order to be able to to me you
need to be mature enough in terms of are
you doing CI in order to be able to do
continuous delivery maybe so so that
that we have it clear what do you mean
by DevOps so that people know what what
continuous delivery is not just okay so
I think about the way I think about
continuous delivery to start with is in
my head I think of it as a pipeline so I
think about the first things you need to
think about is your architecture in the
way that your organization is structured
then it's about quality assurance so all
the things that you currently do to make
sure your software of high quality
automate the hell out of that and then
it's about continuous integration so is
everyone checking in all the time and
we're not merging and we're using trump
based development or using other
patterns in order to do big changes like
branch by obstruction or feature toggles
or whatever it may be and then you get
onto that you've got the data issue like
what are you how are you gonna release
data continuously and then not data
itself but like how you get a really
schema changes and then the last part is
the deployment and the infrastructure
automation and I think DevOps
sits in that last part of deployment and
infrastructure automation but the DevOps
is actually about a cultural change of
dev and ops not being not throwing stuff
over the wall
right so no longer developers get to say
I'm done because I finished developing
I'm now gonna throw this over to the ops
guy and see you later have fun deploying
over the weekend it's now we're
automating that and those guys work
together it's a cultural change that
they work together to automate put this
into production stand up the
environments they know each of us doing
there's no over the wall they're all
responsible for the developers are also
responsible for what goes into
production and so for me DevOps is just
one part of continuous delivery yeah for
me DevOps is the cultural piece and it's
usually a necessary part of continuous
delivery
you really can't achieve what you want
with continuous delivery without having
some DevOps mindset I don't think it's
necessarily true the other way around
like one thing that I think fits within
the DevOps space but isn't necessarily
part of continuous delivery is jad ops
like github talked about they have bots
that their Ops guys use where wouldn't
they need to all of their administration
they basically do through a chat channel
which is really cool in terms of letting
especially like more junior people or
the developer team know what's happening
because as they're releasing to
production or doing whatever it's in the
chat channels so people can see and they
can talk about it but there's actually
BOTS in the channel that are responding
to their commands and deploying mm-hm
so when I summarized it so we have
developers doing code doing maybe data
checking in then there is a continuous
integration happening which is making
software runnable software all of this
running all the tests making sure it's
it's correct and then we move into the
DevOps space kind of in that when the
software is done we continuously make it
ready to be in production by providing
servers configuring servers and
packaging it up well I don't think the
DevOps sort of comes later in the
process I think it's throughout the
whole process it's something that should
be happening even when the developers
rating the code
an example of just people not having the
right answer and developers and
operations not talking to each other I
was working on an application where they
needed geolocation of the home page and
so the developers just took the
requirement from the business and they
want to implement it without talking to
a lot of opps people and thinking it
through a lot and so they implemented
geolocation and rails for the home page
but the problem was it was not really
that performant and so then and later we
had to make the home page cash ball so
basically even though the feature was
done it was effectively unusable because
it was hidden behind cash so I think if
developer and ops were talking earlier
they would have said you really should
be implementing this and something like
varnish up front because that makes much
more sense from a operations perspective
yeah I would agree with that actually so
when I the reason I say that I think
about in terms of a pipeline and then it
said DevOps at the end it's like these
are the practices that have built on top
of each other so we started automating a
lot of the QA so we start we started
doing continuous integration that's more
automation and the work that started
happening in DevOps in terms of these
guys working together and using the same
tools is what built on top of that but
you do need to be thinking about all of
those things right at the start of your
project not just how am I going to
develop this but how is it going to run
in production which is exactly the point
that you had all right so if I'm now
convinced by your arguments that I want
to do continuous delivery and I am on
Windows what decisions do I need to take
to to make this happen so when I gave a
talk last year the way that I broke this
open listen I also broke it up in my
head was thinking about in terms of like
build deploy and then infrastructure
automation and the build part is is the
easiest part in in Windows because
there's so many tools are already out
there
it was the deploy and the automation of
infrastructure that got really painful
yeah so can you shortly mention what was
easy so what
what do you use for build and maybe give
give us a short overview how do I use it
yeah so do you want to talk to this yeah
so with the with it build stuff I mean
you can use things like msbuild and and
in terms of the TI tools out there
there's things like teamcity let's go
you can even use jenkins all of those
things will kick off powershell scripts
or whatever you want there's things like
peace sake which i've started to play
with last year which is a much nicer
than an xml-based language and then
there is there's nice things in terms of
the actual source control management so
you can use get I've been using git on
Windows for the longest time and
whenever I have to go back to TFS it
hurts but why does it hurt it has some
nuances the first one is the fact that
it will do these server-side merges or
at least it did last time I was playing
with it maybe they've made it better
since but this if see people to people
check in at the same time then it will
merge it for you on the server which
doesn't give you that confidence that
you know my build that I think I just
tested on my machine is actually the
same as what's going to get built on the
server on the build server which is a
bit scary it's also quite slow and it's
also people TFS is it's trying to solve
too many problems it's also trying to be
it's trying to be a CI server as well
and it has very everything around that
when I tried yeah it does it tries to do
too much it's a I really I like tools
that do one thing really really well and
work well with other tools that's that's
my preference and I you know and TFS is
not the friendliest when it comes to
that so I guess that's sort of UNIX
philosophy is do one thing and do it
well and write the windows philosophy I
don't know as much about TFS but your
description of it reminds me of
SharePoint which is yeah again another
it's like just to just do one thing and
do it well don't stop trying to do
everything and so as a client last year
and the team was just starting to use
TFS and they were doing this big
presentation all the
things that it can do in the builds and
the way that you can hook it up to your
stories and you can manage your stories
for you agile stories and I think but
there are so many of the tools that can
manage stories better for you
there's better source control management
tools and there's way better build tools
so why don't you just pick one and be
really good at it instead of being
really not so great at all of them and
generally like in terms of build - I've
seen a build that's well it was written
in team builds it took 20 minutes and
I've seen it go down to like three in
another tool just because of how like
cumbersome that the build tool is inside
of canvas or team builders it's called
so we talked about build what is deploy
so I mean one thing that has improved in
the window space before you deploy is to
be able to package things up right so I
mean I have an example right now where
I'm on a client where they literally
have like five solutions in one solution
and so every time you want to make one
change like you have to build the thing
it takes like seven minutes that's just
locally on your machine if I don't want
to compile it takes seven minutes this
is ridiculous and so with things like
NuGet which mean is you know and open
rap is another one like and you get and
we now have packages which is like a
like it is for the wind so now we can
make things that hardly ever change we
can package them off and consume them
and then you can package thing up for
deploy and you can package all the
third-party libraries in terms of deploy
so again there is ms deploy but I've I
found that nine times out of ten you end
up writing stuff in PowerShell
and so that's really as soon as you
start moving into that space it's time
to like learn PowerShell I've the stuff
going on in the infrastructure
automation and deployment space for
Windows seems to be getting interesting
because not that long ago it seemed like
there was nothing
and now Microsoft's really starting to
invest in some of the projects that were
out there so with new get Microsoft
recently in there what's the PowerShell
API something framework oh yeah when I
ran my you talking about oh yeah but
it's the whatever package when RMS
so yeah and the deployment and
infrastructure automation space things
are starting to get interesting so new
gets been around for a while and it's
been fairly successful and recently
Microsoft announced one get which is a
tool they're building into Windows
that's basically going to be Windows
having an official package manager which
is a gigantic change for Windows and
when it launches in the future it might
support other stuff but it's going to
pull from chocolaty it'll have the
chocolate integration so I think in a
lot of ways it's sort of Microsoft
officially endorsing chocolaty what what
is chocolate tree is it can I kind of
think of it like kept ghetto what is it
exactly that's how there is describe it
as it's like it's very inspired by
apt-get and it's supposed to be out get
for Windows so it's basically it's
powered by nougat and PowerShell and
it's essentially a package manager and
silent installer for Windows so if you
want to install like setting up the
stuff for Travis CI I recently they need
on each of their boxes to have get
mercurial and subversion and those
packages actually worked really well
both in chef and PowerShell so I just
have to say in a declarative way I want
get on the box and chef knew to tell
chocolaty and you'd get and chocolaty
decides ok do you need a 32 or 64-bit
installer and then how am I gonna run it
with all of the right flags so that it
just installs silently there's also
Microsoft is doing the desired state
configuration which is parish shell
stuff which is declarative and looks
really interesting when I first saw it I
sort of thought it looked like a
competitor to puppet chef and danceable
and I was like I don't know if we really
need more fragmentation but they
actually when they demoed it they demoed
it along with chef and it looks really
cool because it's more it's declarative
language for saying what you want the
server or servers to be
but it's integrated right into the
operating system and sort of the windows
server management stuff and so rather
than a competing product they're sort of
providing the lower-level
layer that puppet chef and danceable can
call in order to more easily manage
Windows servers yeah because that's
what's been missing for the longest time
um so NuGet know I wasn't new was like
an open source tool there's stuff that
so chocolaty again was like about the
open source community tool so I mean
years ago when I was running a user
group in London alongside a few others
the big part of that community cuz
there's a dotnet user group was the old
net community in it I don't even know if
that's still going but what came out of
that community was things like new new
new get open rap you know people started
building the tools that they did where
they could see we're missing right
especially if you go into a Linux
environment you think we don't have a
tool for that that's not fair I want
people start creating these tools and
what I'm seeing is like Microsoft then
consumes them which is good right as
long as they consume them and don't make
them evil and turn them into T effects
yeah I'm really interested in what
Microsoft doing but I feel like on Linux
we're basically out of state where we're
doing incremental improvements and we've
got a lot of the tools to do all of the
automation and continuous delivery stuff
that we want it seems like on the
Microsoft site they're doing more of a
revolutionary transformation and Windows
starting to do some of this desired
state configuration Windows server core
which is more scaled-down Windows
PowerShell one get all of those things
um
I'm hopeful but I'm a little concerned
with because it's revolutionary and
because it's still somewhat early I'm
not sure how long it'll be before things
on Windows start getting as easy as
they're sort of promising they should be
do we want to go a little bit deeper
into this usage of ansible and and chef
and puppet on windows so what just what
you're talking about it sounds very
promising maybe highlight a little bit
why it is so promising what is what is
making you hope for the future was with
these tools and maybe leverage a little
bit on how you use those tools well one
of the things that I'm not sure I like
about para Shawn desired state
configuration is that it seems like
there is a operation scripting language
and then there is general-purpose
development languages one of the nice
things from you know that DevOps culture
perspective that's happened is that a
lot of the operations tools on the Linux
side have started to use more
general-purpose languages and it makes
it easier for the developers and the
operations guys to pair and go back and
forth so you've got you know the build
and deployment tools they might be in
Ruby and you're building a ruby
application or there's ansible
interesting stuff with Python
so the parish shell desired state
configuration stuff looks interesting
PowerShell has got a lot of interesting
features but with things like chef when
people were first starting to do it they
would include a lot of bash scripting
inside the chef stuff because they were
still figuring it out but then they
decided that was an anti-pattern
you should be trying to do as much just
chef DSL or Ruby stuff it made it more
readable and it made it easier to
collaborate both with developers and I
guess in this case it'll make it easier
for people with Windows backgrounds and
Linux backgrounds to sort of start
collaborating a bit more yeah maybe
let's take one step back
and like makes clear to the people who
have never heard of chef what is it used
for so why do I need chef the puppet
chef and danceable they're all
essentially tools for infrastructure
automation and infrastructure as code
and so it allows you to take the all of
the operations things you're doing and
first of all automate it so that instead
of like this 10 page installation and
configuration guide for the application
and checklist or on book that people
have to go through to do everything that
you have that all automated in a script
and also it's become much more like
normal code and the Sun set we can use
version controls for this stuff and my
there's different ways of setting it up
but I generally like it when the
infrastructure code and the application
code are co-located so they're sort of
urgent and released together and you can
also do a lot more with testing more
easily with the stuff there's great
tools like Test Kitchen and server spec
and food critic and all kinds of things
for chef they're similar tools I think
the great thing about them is the
desired state part so rather than just
being a shell scripts that's going go
and make these changes on the server
it's like it's telling the server what
it should look like and I really like
that about them so you you tell the
server I want you to have an AI is
running on port 80 yeah exactly and for
and a big part of the problem it's been
in Windows and even when you're using
chef and puppet when I was doing it last
year is that for a big part of it you
have to go and do like go out into an
exact welcome basically run by
PowerShell script which is just like go
out and run a bash scripting and I know
that the support has been improving all
the time but I'm not sure it's at the
point where you don't have to do that
anymore maybe this is these new tools
are going to provide that way you don't
have to keep executing out to PowerShell
yeah thank you at least in the the
previews Microsoft has out of some of
these new versions of the tools that
it's definitely getting there but I
don't think it's generally available yet
you talked about testing your chef on
and puppet scripts what do you test do
you really fire up a server run the
puppet script and tests what is working
or yes so there's just like developing
an application you usually want a couple
of different types of tests and so there
is you can do unit testing where you're
just sort of mocking things and you
don't have to fire up real servers so
the advantages it runs really fast
although I think most of the issues were
doing with this stuff that sort of
testing won't tend to catch because it's
all integration stuff like if you say
install iis and you just mock the fact
that is install successfully but then
when you go to actually run it you find
that like you don't have working network
connectivity on the server yet and it
can't pull down packages that it needs
in order to do things so unless I'm
extending Jeff itself adding new types
of resources I would use unit testing
there but the majority of what I'm doing
is integration testing where I'll spend
a spin up a real server either as a VM
using VirtualBox or hyper-v or on the
cloud using Asia or AK space or
something and actually run all of my
chef there and then you can use
something like server expect to verify
the results so with server expect for
example you said install is on port 80
you can actually write a generic test
that says there should be an HTTP server
on port 80 and the way server specs
written it doesn't even care if it's
Linux or Windows or iis or nginx you're
just writing the general requirement I
need
serving a webpage on port 80 so the
tools that I use for testing I think
that in terms of making continuous to
live really start happening on Windows
the most important tools for me to see
them start to support Windows are the
tools that give developers or operations
people a sandbox where they can start
playing around with different things
like chef for desired state
configuration or whatever one of the
great things that's happened recently is
that vagrant sean neil the guy who did
vagrant windows which was originally a
plugin he worked with the vagrant core
team and with microsoft and they
actually added hyper-v support and to
vagrant and they put a lot of effort
into window stuff unfortunately hyper-v
only runs on Windows so that helps
people already on Windows or on extra
windows VMs I'm still sort of struggling
to get some of my own VirtualBox images
but VirtualBox and vagrant on Windows
does seem to be working as well but it's
not quite ready for Windows cloud stuff
yet because it's they added the win RM
support but it's not secure and vagrant
yet so if you're just talking to local
VM that's ok if you're talking over the
Internet to the cloud you probably want
some real encryption and similarly test
kitchen I think is another project that
will let people experiment and start
testing you know if you want to try
something and desired state
configuration and then you want to try
moving over to chef and make sure it has
the same result or if you want to test
like multiple versions of Windows so
maybe Server 2012 and server core 2012
Test Kitchen will let you do that stuff
but unfortunately they don't quite have
Windows support there yet
maybe because it was very plus plastic
in the one talk you gave Rachel can you
contrast the two concept of a snowflake
server and the Phoenix server and what
what this actually means in Windows and
I'm not sure if it's Phoenix server on
Windows is even possible well I mean a
snowflakes over is that you know snow
fit the idea that the analogy is that
snowflakes are unique individual things
and no two are the same and service I
think not just on Windows in general
used to be like that right people would
go off and write scripts and make
changes or they'd go through those big
run books and they're just like they're
constantly just adding change to the to
the what how the server is configured
and what's on there and over time you
know you didn't change it or do anything
to it because you don't know if that
thing that's on it it's actually useful
or is it do we need it I don't know no
one touch it we don't wanna break
production you said that Outlook became
the configuration management system kind
of oh yeah yeah yeah back in the day
yeah I mean actually I'm I'm on a client
right now where they're they're still in
that old way of releasing where they're
it's email driven so they have the run
book and everything but then I see on
release date I see like 20 emails going
back and forth like I've done step four
to seven now you can do step eight and
nine like and so people are still doing
that out there in the industry for sure
the idea of the Phoenix server is
something you know that you can destroy
and then pull back up whenever and I
think is it is it Amazon that has the
chaos monkey on Netflix
yeah well who one of those guys but yeah
Netflix has the chaos monkey where they
you know they go around and just burn
servers and and they should be able to
spin them back up whenever because
everything in terms of the configuration
management and the desired state is in
source control so you can just spin that
back up so that's that's the difference
can we do it yet on Windows I think I
think you can automate most of the stuff
on Windows now but you are gonna be
doing a lot of PowerShell to a certain
extent to call out to like win RM
one of the bigger problems is actually
all the it's all the other software that
you often have to put on systems that
don't have any kind of unified package
management our way of automating the
deployment like some of the tools that
you have to put on Windows machines it's
often literally like it's a click click
through to get it installed and that's
that's kind that's hard to automate so
to a certain extent depending on what
you need to have on your server you
could have phoenix service but if you've
got all these weird and wonderful like
tools and things that you have to have
on your machine that don't have a great
way of being automatable if that's a
word then it's going to be very
difficult and that's one of the that's
one of the challenges in Windows is all
those extra stuff that you have to put
on I think it's definitely possible on
Windows because with Phoenix servers
even if you have things you can't
automate and you're doing manual steps
it's about having images as artifacts
and so as long as at the end of the day
if you can create an image and when
you're just sort of stamping servers
from that so you say whether I need five
servers there 20 servers and production
I just do it from this image if server
12 has given me problems then I don't
try to fix it I just destroy it and I
create a new one because it's easier and
I think generally the support for that
imaging stuff is there like you can
definitely do custom images on all of
the cloud providers for Windows stuff
and with Asia you can even export VMs
running in hyper-v and move them on to
the cloud
another important project though there's
Packer which is made by the same people
as vagrant and it's sort of the
counterpart in the vagrant is for
creating development environments and
Packer is for creating server images for
whatever platforms and I know that we
have recorded or we we are about to
record a show was the guy who did the
grant so maybe you can check that out
I'm not sure if it comes out after
before that but we have more on vagrant
okay but there's a Packer windows
project right now that you can use to
create base VMs forever
in Windows and you could use essentially
the same technology to create customized
ones for applications one of the issues
there right now though is that Packer
doesn't have one RM support yet so in
order to really use Packer windows right
now what they do is they install SSH
onto their Windows servers and then they
Stewie use PowerShell but they do all
this
PowerShell over SSH instead of one RM
Wow but you are so you're talking about
a great it's another patent say images I
didn't actually think about that um
nothing like an image just as an
artifact so that's something that you
can also like check in and you can take
through your delivery pipeline this is
the image that this is going with as
well yeah for me one of the big gaps
that I'm curious if we're ever going to
see it Windows equivalent anytime soon
as docker because if you take image of
what is docker docker is similar to
images but it's more layered the way I
understand it and so you just have a
small core server and then docker drops
and like you can have sort of a shared
image that has all of your common stuff
and then you can have like a application
layer on top of that for your
application specific stuff but I think
the big advantages with docker is that
they're much smaller because of them
doing these layered images and shared
images so if you're trying to version
images and you're deploying ten times a
day and each deployment like every time
I've created a Windows image it's been
four gigs so storing and transferring
four gigs over the network every time I
want to do new releases they're pulled
down especially for developer machines
if I want to pull down the latest ement
there it's definitely more than a couple
of changes to a puppet script yeah you
have mentioned a lot about PowerShell I
haven't done a lot of PowerShell work
and I guess most of our listeners
haven't either so can you tell us about
PowerShell and contrast it maybe a
little bit against bash or a
general-purpose language
so I can't really contrast it against
Bosch because I'm not a lunatic person
but I mean PowerShell was when it first
came out was just amazing because we
never really had that ability on Windows
before to be able to do that the level
of automation that we have with
PowerShell and and I actually said last
year that it was like an ugly an ugly
long way tonight and then got a lot of
backlash from Mac's people like actually
you can make PowerShell really nice you
can make it really oh oh you can you can
actually do nice things with you can
make PowerShell you know behave well and
I think it's one of those languages
that's like that where you can do
horrible ugly things with it but you
can't actually make it behave well I
know I haven't actually written that
much PowerShell I've just been using all
of the PowerShell based tools but one
thing I do know that's very interesting
compared to bash is they both have all
of this support for pipelining where you
can take the output of one program and
use it as the input for the next one and
chain things together to make a more
complete solution but the difference is
in bash and on all of the Linux shells
your piping texts from one program to
the next and on PowerShell it actually
does it with objects and so for some
things like if you've got a table and
you want to get certain rows you don't
even think about it when you come from
the bash Linux background but now that I
think about that more with parish shell
and like I see a lot of bash commands
that are really hacky and that don't
have any intent at all so if you see
like cut - F 1 - D comma or whatever
it's because they're sort of trying to
get rows of comma separated values out
of the output of one program where with
PowerShell you can just say give me this
row or this column of values or treat it
more as random access objects and what
kind of programs or scripts you write in
PowerShell so is it is it all about
automating existing programs like you
would do in Linux and
or do you really write long scripts in
it I mean you could it's really about
automating the environment I mean I
don't know if you were asking if you
would use it for another purpose which I
don't think you would because there are
a lot of nice along which is out there
for just general purpose programming the
power of PowerShell is is the things
that it lets you do and the way that you
can talk to like Windows remoting and
the power of it is that is its power
right is the ability to be it it will
automate the environments and be able to
talk to different parts of of Windows so
it's it's fine I mean some people love
it
for the reason that there wasn't that
there before and so it's amazing but
then when you look at in contrast to
what you can do in Linux environments
with the tools that you have there like
chef chef it that's a new one chef
boomys ansible and and all these things
it's you're like oh it's actually not as
great as those because you can't have
that desired state you're still doing
he's still essentially scripting but the
desired state configuration that is pure
PowerShell that's stuff the cleaner it's
I thought it was them okay my bad I
thought it was chef and puppet did the
desired state they're like it's supposed
to be in this state
Microsoft is providing a desired state
configuration API that's written in
PowerShell puppet and chef can use that
as a provider so that they're
integrating through PowerShell or at
least through the same API - so you
still write the declarative desired
state and puppet or chef and it maps it
to the PowerShell version of that which
is essentially equivalent so if you tell
chef
I want Windows feature is installed
rather than it saying ok in order to do
that I need to get this installer or
whatever it just tells windows
I want this windows feature enabled all
right it's still using PowerShell under
the hood basic thing is what you're
saying you think yeah they they will be
yeah this stuff's still because I think
that that's that that's the thing
PowerShell gives you that ability that
that all the other tools have to use but
it isn't it isn't it isn't wherewhere
where they are in the Linux world as far
as I understand so as I understand it
you could say PowerShell is a
programming language to facilitate
communication between other tools on
Windows well I think one interesting
thing with PowerShell and when I was
talking about the revolutionary changes
versus incremental so raychel Road and
one of her articles that we need to tell
people we need better tools and
automation on Windows and that doesn't
mean a GUI for everything we can't have
all of these GUI driven installers and
so I thought you know the cultural
change is just getting all of the admins
and users used to the fact that we need
to have you know something like one get
essentially where you can just install
something quickly from the command line
but what Microsoft has been doing is
they still write all of the the gooey
stuff for Windows server management and
all of those things but they've said the
GUI is built on top of the same
PowerShell API now and so they're saying
anything you can do through the GUI
because it's being driven by PowerShell
you can do anything the exact same stuff
and without using the GUI and hopefully
I know definitely Microsoft with their
own products have been doing that I'm
hoping everybody adopts that this
becomes it's very scripted it's Annie
it's need for everyone to follow suit
because I mean the blockers that I've
seen really is when there's some
third-party tool or something that has
to be installed with it and there's no
way to automate that you know when the
vendor vendor created it the they
weren't thinking about this in terms of
how we're gonna automate deployments
like no we've given you a tool and
here's the instructions for how to
install it because back in the day
people used to do it manually and that's
fine and it's getting it's the cultural
change which it's great to see Microsoft
sort of paving the way because I think
if
they don't pave the way the bigger
vendors won't follow them like people in
the old connect community we can keep
writing as many tools as we want around
the ecosystem but it's it's gonna be
it's hard if Microsoft doesn't adopt
that change because then the vendors
won't follow suit and that's what we
need to happen maybe following on top of
that the when I hear you talk you you
mention all of open-source tools but
they're still always this but it has to
be approved by Microsoft is that how it
is or can there be really an open-source
tool without Microsoft there there are
open-source tools without Microsoft that
people use I think it's the tricky thing
is is a lot of Microsoft tools are used
in the enterprise and they're often much
slower to adopt change and they want
things like you know licensing
agreements and who's gonna look after it
if it breaks and all this kind of stuff
and whereas open-source tools are
literally you know people build
something that they need and they share
it and other people like yeah I use this
too it's cool and and the support comes
from the community and I mean I was in
an architecture working group last week
trying to get the microphone actual even
vendor tool agreed by the client and
there and all they want to know is like
who's gonna support it if it goes wrong
and so yeah as a developer I'm just
gonna if something's wrong or I don't
understand how to do something I'm just
gonna google it and look on Stack
Overflow and talk to the community or
I'm gonna email people that you know
work in that community and I have this
problem can you help me and the
enterprise doesn't work like that they
want all this extra vendor support and
so it's actually harder to get those
open-source tools adopted in bigger
enterprise I think outside of that you
know when people if you're outside of
the enterprise and you have more freedom
being really definitely using these
tools you know people were using new get
until and when Microsoft adopted it and
also chocolaty like it sounds like
they're also going to adopt that that's
also from an open source still Microsoft
didn't create it but if people are
starting to use it in the community it's
great if they take it on board or adopt
it or support it because it means that
then we can start using these tools in
the enterprise which is which is what we
want but it still sounds to me like when
you as an open source tool get like
supported by Microsoft that's the way
when you get the the big usages I think
that is that
just the the nature of the beast of
working in in enterprise environments
there's a much bigger cultural change
there that needs to happen in terms of
how people think about software
development and and how you get support
and there so many enterprise
organizations are used to it's a tool if
it breaks I'm gonna get support for it
and the way that software development
has evolved is this different to that
it's more about here's the tool that
solves this problem really well and does
an entire community of millions of
developers out there who are also
probably using this tool who can help me
if I have a problem and it's a mindset
change as well one of the things I
really like about open source tools that
I think people should keep in mind when
they're making their purchase decisions
is the support from the community is
such a huge thing and I think the most
visible thing is some of the tools with
really large user conferences so you
look at Jeff conf and puppet conf and
with these tools if you want to know the
best practices and how other people are
doing having those things you can you
don't even have to go to those events
most of those all of those videos are
available on YouTube and you can go and
watch the actual users explaining what
they're doing where they had problems
how to use it with a lot of the
commercial tools because it's not always
that open the only people a lot of times
that you can get to tell you the right
way to do it or give you a demo and show
you how the project works is the vendor
the people actually trying to sell to
you which totally ties you in I mean I
can't remember I mean I obviously yeah
at Google things every day all the time
in my job and I can't remember the last
time I google something and there wasn't
an answer or like ten answers or in
Stack Overflow you just go to the one
that got uploaded the most right there's
always a way to solve the problem when I
first started developing like like 14
years ago whenever it was you know that
Google wasn't like it was now they
didn't I don't even think Google was
around we were using Yahoo and
but you know if you had a problem it's
ages to find it and and in the windows
world it was all like MSDN and the
licences and you had to go and search
through all of that stuff and you know
how to find the one way to do it now
you know you google something there's
like a million ways to do it you'll find
a video or someone's done it and
especially with these big tools that
like everyone is consuming and so it's
actually it's hard to convince the
architects and people in the enterprise
that that's actually better then just
being locked down by a vendor it's a
black box you don't know how it works
you've got a problem you you know you
log it you maybe they'll fix it if it's
a priority you know it's back and forth
whereas oh I'll just let me just google
that and I could probably fix this today
right so do you have some good ways to
make the argument you just said is
necessary so what what should I tell my
boss if he wants to buy a big tool which
is very expensive and needs new GUI
installer so the way that I approach
that is looking at using examples where
I know that other people have used an
open-source tool versus you know a big -
I mean something like a serviceable
Enterprise Service bus is a great
example of that there's all these big
vendors selling big enterprise service
process whereas there's tons of tools
out there that can do you know messaging
just as easily that aren't so expensive
and you know the support is in the
community you can also put I mean for
the bit for the business side winning
that argument can be a case if
something's like I look at you know when
when was the last check-in on that tool
right so he actually actively being
worked on because that tells you that
people are playing like doing making
changes to it fixing it right now and
that's great you know how many
contributors is it God how many people
are using it you know you can find out
this information get some idea of like
how well used it is and how big the
community is and you can sort of put
those figures together and give you know
help them make a better decision in
terms of choose this open-source tool
which if we if it breaks we can fix it
because that's what always the question
that we get say what if it breaks who's
gonna fix it it's like we can fix it
it's an open-source tool we can we check
it out and make the changes ourselves
and then we can do a pull request and
maybe maybe I'll fix it for everyone
else you know
but it's it's a total different mindset
change and there is a lot of convincing
that we have to do in that way and then
like culturally getting them out of the
vendor support mindset as well yeah I
think when I've seen people doing
purchase decisions they usually have
different categories they're looking at
they'll have a checklist or matrix or
whatever to fill out and so they'll
always be like price licensing and a big
focus on features and I think we just
need to remind people and that culture
should be at least as emphasized as the
feature set probably and it's definitely
important to look at you know how active
are the projects how many other
companies are using it what are their
user conferences and things like and for
the gap and feature is you're really
looking for either a vendor or a
community that you can partner with not
just something that necessarily solves
here current needs but one that's going
to be able to handle your needs two
years from now and so if you look at
okay if there's a gap in the features
how long will it take the vendor for you
to convince them that it's needed and
they should put some effort into it and
then for them to finally deliver it
versus the open source community and if
you have the skills if you have if you
say like oh this one feature is a deal
breaker we need it then you could say
well how much effort would it actually
take us for to implement the features we
need and then give it back to the
community and I think there's a thing
one of the issues that I face is when
they're talking about you know what's
gonna happen in a few years is we don't
we have no idea what's gonna what the
state of the ecosystem is gonna be in a
few years and so many organizations
large organizations you know they're
only just moving off XP right and it's
like there you need to constantly be
thinking about upgrading and and the
culture of improvement and upgrade needs
to happen within the teams and when you
start to create that culture then you
can start asking questions answer
questions like well
we built that in like let us fix it
let's add it to it rather than we're
just gonna hand that off to somebody
else and we're just gonna keep pumping
out cold it's like we need to start
thinking about how how does our system
work in production
what kind of we're gonna need me to be
making continuous changes and get out of
the mindset of okay I've got you know a
two-year plan and this is my project
it's going to get delivered in two years
and it's never gonna change like that
that is a complete fallacy we know that
the software is gonna keep changing and
so that needs to be part of the culture
of like we know it's gonna change we
want to be able to make changes the
vendor might not be able to move as fast
as those but you know we can move that
fast because we have we're gonna we need
that feature we're gonna build it or
we're gonna find it another open-source
tool that they can do that feature for
us this brings me to maybe a little bit
provocative final question is why don't
you guys just use Linux it's because we
don't always have the choice so there
are tools out there that only run on
Windows you know at for example the
client I'm on right now was built a
specific tool they're only runs on
Windows it's been running for 10 years
you know we're not gonna turn around and
say you know that tool that you've been
building for like ten years so Windows
sucks so why don't you just rebuild the
whole thing so that we can put it onto a
Linux environment it's more it's more
about you just you don't always have the
choice specific you so in a lot of cases
you need to be on Windows so let's make
it better rather than just being like oh
this doesn't work and throwing the baby
out with the bathwater right it's like
our windows suck some don't they're not
gonna do anything on anymore we're gonna
rewrite all the applications that that
need to live on windows so it's I've
been in Windows 4 for 10 years and it's
it's not going anywhere
so we have to fix some of the issues
that are in there yeah for me I think if
you actually have a choice between being
on Windows or being on Linux then I
would usually choose Linux but I think
even for new applications it's not just
as the legacy stuff it's about who are
the users going to be
who are the developers available who are
the operations people so
if you've done a dotnet organization for
a long time and you're writing tools for
an organization that uses Windows
desktops then it doesn't necessarily
make sense to retrain everyone even for
when there's no legacy and you get to
start something new yeah it's about
constraints right so you've got these
constraints you have to do it so we have
to make it better and it sounds like you
know I'm really happy the even in the
last to two years what's happening in
the community you know the community
tools they're being built at the
progress that Microsoft is making as
well in adopting and going like actually
running with them and supporting things
like chocolaty and or taking it on board
and using it in their tools is this is
all promising it's it's it's going to
get better all right so I will want to
now give you the opportunity to ask her
to to ask for the question I should have
asked and then answer it I got a
question for you before that okay
have you used pester do you know
anything about birthday yeah I've used
it not not in massive anger when I
realized that you I was like so must be
a tool for the most be a TDD tool for
like unit testing I mean for a
powershell and then I thought worker was
like yeah I wrote one so yeah I've used
it a little bit it's it's cool it's
gives you the ability the ability to do
unit testing in PowerShell which is it's
nice because I think well for me one of
the great things about unit testing is
it changes at least if you do TDD it
changes the way that you think about how
you develop your code and I think having
a tool like that and changes the way
that people write the PowerShell scripts
so rather than just bashing out like
right I'm just gonna write this line to
make this work and then I'm gonna write
this to make this work it's like you
actually being more like thinking more
clearly about ok what do I need it to do
and then writing a test for that and so
I think that's more it's more about
behavior and I mean it's great to have
unit testing but I think it's bringing
out better behavior because one of the
things that I've seen coming to systems
where people like yeah we've got
PowerShell scripts and you go in there
and then
and they're really hard to read and then
you know they doesn't have well named
variables or anything in there and it's
all that stuff oh my god didn't we solve
these problems in just coding years ago
you know why are we why have we gone
into a new language and just forgotten
everything we knew about you know
encapsulation and how we break things
open how we make how we make things
understandable and readable and and that
would be I mean it seems like for the
foreseeable future PowerShell is here to
stay and so that's at least writing
nicely did you have another question I'm
trying to think of any question or just
some last words you would like to say
for me I talked about it a little
earlier but the question I would have
asked myself was what are the most
important DevOps projects going on for
Windows right now and for me it's really
like I said all about being able to have
sandboxes where developers and Ops guys
can play around with things they can
collaborate so for me the most important
projects are getting complete support
for Windows and vagrant Microsoft has
won a big barrier to vagrant even though
it's mostly functionally complete is
trying to get the images for Windows so
Microsoft has released a couple of
different images but it's like the
images they released in the form of a
vagrant box is only for hyper-v so you
can only use it on Windows and then they
have other images that are just like
regular VM images so you have to build
your own vagrant boxes out of them using
Packer doing it manually so when I
wanted to create a VM that I could use
to test on Windows it takes me a couple
of hours just to create it and then the
problem is once I've done that you would
hope I would say for everyone else the
time but because no one's I guess either
restricted or just everyone's unsure of
how the licensing works for Windows
nobody shares these so everybody has to
waste the same half a day to build their
own VM
they have vagrants a very important
project and then like I said Test
Kitchen because if you're doing multiple
different versions of Windows or Windows
and Linux Test Kitchen lets you validate
a whole set of servers different roles
if you've got a application where you've
got like infrastructure automation for
web nodes versus database nodes so you
can use the test kitchen for that yeah I
mean I would I would totally agree with
that I think one of the biggest blockers
to doing continuous delivery on Windows
is the ability to spin up machines and
start making changes and testing locally
as quickly as possible because that's
what you want you want that fast
feedback and that's the really as soon
as people start we start talking about
that in Windows environments it's like I
just there's like a big sigh that
happens inside me because I'm like I
know okay we're here we're gonna go down
this fun journey again I'm we're gonna
work for even if we could get the right
image and spin everything up it's like
there's not just there's licensing
issues with you've got all these vendor
tools and you know they've only got
they've got one in production in one in
QA and you know but I need to be able to
test it all the time whenever I want
yeah I think there's that and then I
think getting the vendors to follow suit
would be would be a great win as well I
actually think just in general the the
way that the vendor over the old school
like vendor relationships and the way
that they they currently operate and
that kind of black boxes I feel that it
just needs to change as a whole and we
need to start encouraging this API
driven way of doing things and then to
have tools that interoperate well with
all the tools and tools that do one
thing well and stop this they crazy
that's by this great big tool that you
can only deploy once and it takes a GUI
to do it and all these kinds of things
so yeah that would be nice all right so
where can people find out more about
Windows continuous delivery and
automation you've written a couple of
blocks
yes a couple of blogs I wrote on for
works come from last year and actually
the interesting thing was some of the
comments in the bottom linked to a ton
more articles that people have written
and there's a lot of people there doing
good stuff and don't know if you can
talk to where people can find out the
infinite list of realm would get in what
you were talking about this does it
Microsoft or - yeah we can provide -
yeah be good all right
it's what's the best way to get in touch
with you Twitter Email yeah you can
tweet meets that Rachael Leigh Cook I'm
working on a ton of open source stuff
right now so if you want to see more of
what I'm up to github is actually a
great way to find me and there's an
email address out there
alright and thank you very much for
being on the show we I will provide you
with all the links and all the stuff we
mentioned in the show notes so you don't
have to type from listening we would
actually SSE read you like to get
feedback from you so maybe you write a
comment or a review in iTunes and tell
us what you like the most and the least
in this episode or something like that
in this terms we are saying goodbye this
is your harness for messy review thanks
for the show thank you thanks thanks for
listening to s-see radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise su
radio by clicking the de crédit
delicious or / bad buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on
so other listeners can respond to your
comments as well this and all of the
episodes of se radio is licensed under
the creative commons 2.5 license please
see the looks at the details thanks
again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]